Guide to the Clayton Stafford Papers, 1911-1981
Department of Special Collections
Clayton Stafford Papers,
1911-1981
Special Collections M434
Stafford, Clayton
1.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Mrs. Clayton Stafford, 1985 and 1986.
BIOGRAPHY
Clayton I. Stafford was born September 17, 1903 in Albany, New York and died in June of 1981 in Los Altos, California. He studied engineering in college and, after a brief tour in the Navy in the 1920s, joined the Pacific Company in 1930. He served in WWII in the Army from 1942 to 1946 working on radio research and development. During his life Stafford lived mainly in the San Francisco area and was married three times to Jean Adams, Adelaide Fairbanks Ellsworth, and Ruth Homer. His last wife, Ruth, survived him, and is responsible for the selection and donation of the collection, as well as the many notes throughout.
Clayton Stafford is primarily remembered as a writer and poet from the 1950s and 1960s. He published several works in periodicals and a book of poetry, The Swan and the Eagle, in 1968 (collection includes TMS). He was a close friend and contemporary of such notable writers as Howard Baker, J.V. Cunningham, Janet Lewis, and Yvor Winters. The collection includes some of Stafford's correspondence, as well as works by these and other writers. Stafford was also an avid book collector, gardener, and researcher and kept many notebooks on these subjects, which are included in the collection. Stafford's autobiography, Fragments of an Autobiography, was published posthumously in 1983 (collection includes TMS).
SCOPE AND CONTENT
Poems, an unfinished novela, an autobiography, and notes by Clayton Stafford. Poems by and correspondence with Howard Baker, J.V. Cunningham, Barbara Gibbs, Francis Golffing, Janet Lewis, Henry Ramsey, Ann Stanford, and Yvor Winters.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I: works by Clayton Stafford
  - "The Swan and the Eagle and other poems" TMS (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - miscellaneous poetry, 1931-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - miscellaneous prose (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - copy of original TMS of "Fragments of an Autobiography" with corrections (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - TMS "Fragments of an Autobiography" copyright 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - earliest draft TMS "The Figurehead" with corrections (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - middle draft TMS "The Figurehead" with corrections (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - final draft TMS "The Figurehead" with corrections, abandoned 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - notes for "The Figurehead" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - TMS "The Pioneers," play adopted from novel by James Fenimore Cooper (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Argonaut, (1930-1931), articles by Stafford (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The New Republic (1934), poetry by Stafford and colleagues (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - miscellaneous notes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - translations by Stafford of other's poetry (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: personal ephemera of Clayton Stafford
  - correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - military service documents (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - photos (1911-1945) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - photos (1941-1964) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - photos (1978-1979) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "In Memoriam," memorial pamphlet on the death of Stafford, 6/23/81 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Neutra House, owned by Stafford (built 1939, Los Altos) (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series III: journals, notebooks, and lists
  - journal (1942) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - class notes and notes on books (1957-1966) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Garden Notebook (1950-1981) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - trip log, trip to England (1969) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Stafford family genealogy study (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - book lists of Staffords' library (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - miscellaneous notebooks (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - miscellaneous notes (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Ruth Stafford (Clayton's third wife)
  - correspondence (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - particular items & photos with notes from Ruth (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series: V: colleagues and friends of Clayton Stafford
  - Ames, Van Meter (articles) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Baker, Howard (poetry, correspondence, etc.) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "The Gyroscope" by Howard Baker (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cunningham, J.V. (poetry, etc.) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - McClelland, John Mill (memorial resolution) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ramsey, Henry (poetry) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Winters, Yvor (poetry, notes, articles concerning Winters, etc.) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Southern Review, Yvor Winters Issue (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - others' poetry (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - others' prose (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - others' articles (Box 3, Folder 14)